Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף *daf* is צדי *Tzadi*, בבא
מציעא *Bava Metzia* 90. We pick up on the very last line
of פ"ט עמוד ב' *pe tet amud bet*, תנו רבנן *Tana Rabanan*,
and our learning should be in the זכות *zechut* of our חיילים
*chayalim* and חיילות *chayolot*, and also memory, as today's Memorial Day, as
I record this, of all of the American soldiers who gave their
lives to protect all of us living in America and to protect
our life and liberty here. All right, so we are still in
the middle of the discussion of the right of the worker to
eat when working in the crops and the prohibition against muzzling an
ox or any animal when it is threshing, and the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* of course has abstracted that to include a wide array of
cases. תנו רבנן *Tana Rabanan*: פרות המרכסות בתבואה *Parat hameraksot batvuah*, cows
that are threshing, walking over grain, and there's a whole debate of
the ראשונים *Rishonim* what this talks about, but it's clear because on
the simple sense, this sounds to be like a classic case of
threshing where the prohibition would apply, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
about to say that the prohibition does not apply. So רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* say we're talking about a type of
grain that it has already reached the stage of being obligated in
תרומות ומעשרות trumos umasros, *trumot umasrot*. So therefore, as we learned before,
the law of prohibiting muzzling a cow does not apply once it's
reached גמר מלאכה gmar melacha *gmar melacha* for תרומות ומעשרות trumos umasros
*trumot umasrot*. It's not exactly easy to understand how that is the
case here while it's still being threshed, but that's what they say.
רמב"ם *Rambam* gives a different explanation, that they're not intentionally being used
for threshing, they just happen to be walking over it. Anyway, that's
that case, פרות המרכסות בתבואה *Parat hameraksot batvuah*. Now top of צ'
עמוד א' *tzadi amud alef*, which is going to be what we
much more focused on: והדשות בתרומה ובמעשר *v'hadasas b'truma u'ma'aser*,
and cows that are threshing grain that is תרומה truma *truma* and
מעשר maser. *ma'aser*. Okay, אינו עובר משום בל תחסום *eino over mishum
bal tachsom*, you do not transgress the prohibition of muzzling. So we're
going to be focused on the תרומה truma *truma* and מעשר maser?
*ma'aser*. Now of course you might be thinking, if the grain is
already תרומה truma *truma* and מעשר maser, *ma'aser*, תרומות ומעשרות trumos umasros,
*trumot umasrot* have been separated and now they're walking or doing some
type of a מלאכה melakhah *melacha* on this grain, well then that
means it's already obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumos umasros *trumot umasrot*. So
it's reached the stage of גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha* for תרומות ומעשרות
trumos umasros *trumot umasrot*, where this prohibition does not apply. So we'll
see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it is possible to separate תרומות
ומעשרות trumos umasros, *trumot umasrot* before it becomes obligated. The state of
obligation, as I mentioned, by grain is when it's been threshed and
winnowed and put into a pile, and once it reaches that
state, it's forbidden to eat from it even עראי *arai*, even like
a little nibbling or whatever, until תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros *trumot umasrot*
are separated. At an earlier stage, it has the potential of separating
תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros? *trumot umasrot*, and if you do, it takes
effect, but it is not yet obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros
*trumot umasrot*, so that gives a little bit more latitude in terms
of eating from it עראי *arai* and in a temporary type of
way. Okay, so let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says. אינו עובר משום בל תחסום *eino over mishum bal tachsom*,
אבל מפני מראית העין *aval mipnei maris ayin*, but that it should
not look bad like people should not think, the מראית *maris* means
the vision of the eye, it's not bad, it's not עין רעה
*ayin ra'ah*, like right, it's not עין הרע *ayin hara*. Okay, because
of how things appear, that people will think, won't realize it's תרומות
ומעשרות trumos u'maasros, *trumot umasrot*, or whatever the case before was by
מרכסות *meraksot*, and they'll think you're transgressing or that it will give
them license not to do it for their cow, to muzzle their
cow. מביא בול מאותו המין *mavi bul me'oto hamin*, you bring like
a handful from that type of from the same thing that they're
threshing on, ותולה לו בטרכסלין שבפיה *v'tolo lo b'trakselin shebefiha*, and you
put it in a basket right by its mouth so it will
have what to be munching from as it is as it is
threshing. Not exactly clear to me a couple of things. First of
all, if it's eating from this basket,
then what, then you're not muzzling it? So it has the ability
to eat from the grain, but because the basket is so much
closer, it's going to choose to eat from the basket? I guess
that must be what it is, because if this basket were right
over its mouth and muzzling it, it would still look like you're
muzzling. And then the other question is just an economic one, which
is how does it work out that it
is better for you financially to give it from that stuff and
to put it in the basket than to just let it nibble
and eat? I guess maybe there's a limited amount, you know, that's
in the basket. Okay, so let's take a look. So רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai *Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai* אומר omer
*omer*, מביא כרשינין ותולה לה שהכרשינין יפות לה מן הכל *mavi karshinin
v'tolo lo shekarshinin yafot la min hakol*. You give it not from
that thing that it's threshing in, but you give it vetch, which
is a type of a thing that grew that was very much
eaten by animals, as we see says כרשינין *karshinin* is better than
any other thing. Which is very nice that you're taking care of
your animal,
but how does it address the מראית העין *maris ayin*? Wouldn't the
מראית העין *maris ayin* be addressed better if it was eating the
same type of a thing that was right there that it was
threshing? look like you're addressing that right of the animal to be
eating from what it's threshing? So not exactly clear to me. All
right, ורמינהי *v'reminhi*, anyway, that's the הלכה halakhah? *halacha* about תרומות trumos
*trumas* and מעשר maser. *maaser*. That if it's תרומה truma *truma* that
it's that it's פטור *patur*, that it's exempt. There doesn't exactly explain
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* why it's exempt, but basically רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* say, although רש"י Rashi *Rashi* has more
than it seems to be more than one explanation, is because it
says לא תחסום lo tachsom שור בדישו shor b'disho. *Lo sachsom shor
b'disho* in its threshing and the בדישו bedisho *b'disho*'s a sense of
like ownership. So the so since תרומה truma *truma*, even if it's
the cow of a כהן kohen, *kohen* and you know a כהן
kohen *kohen* can feed his cow תרומה truma *truma* grain, assuming that
it's that it's not fit for מאכל אדם *maachal adam* for people
to eat from it and so on, but it's not considered to
be something that you have total freedom with and total license with
and therefore it doesn't satisfy the בדישו bedisho *b'disho*. And similarly by
מעשר maser *maaser* we'll see that we're going to be talking about
מעשר שני maser sheni, *maaser sheini* and מעשר שני maaser sheni *maaser
sheini* has to be brought up to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and according
to some opinions it's considered ממון גבוה mamon gavoh. *mamon gavoha* and
not your money. So that's why the, these, that's why those two
are are excepted, although it's quite fascinating that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
never explains why. But if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot*, he says like this: first narrow line, he says וניראה דטעמא
משום דכתיב דישו disho דמשמע הראוי לו ומעשר ממון גבוה mamon gavoh
הוא *V'nireh d'taama mishum d'ksiv disho dimashma haraoy lo u'maaser mamon gavoha
hu*. So
מעשר maser. *maaser* is considered to be belonging to God, just you
have the right to eat from it for מעשר שני maaser sheni
*maaser sheini*, you bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. ותרומה נמי לישראל
אסור ליתן לפני בהמתו *U'truma nami l'Yisrael asur litein lifnei behemsu*. And
for תרומה truma, *truma* a Jew, a non-כהן kohen *kohen* can't feed
תרומה truma, *truma* grain to his animal. ואפילו כהן kohen דוקא כרשינין
*V'afilu kohen davka karshinin* and but even for a כהן kohen, *kohen*
only this כרשינין *karshinin* that was mentioned, this vetch, שהוא מאכל בהמה
*shehu maachal beheima*, which is the food of animal food, מותר להאכיל
ולא חטים משום הפסד תרומה truma, *mutar l'haachil v'lo chitim mishum hefsed
truma*. Okay, and therefore because you don't have the license to do
it, it's not saying because you transgress a prohibition by giving it
to your animal, what he's saying is since you don't have total
license to do with it what you want, or maybe it's not
the בדישו bedisho, *b'disho* of the ox, it's not something that the
ox
normally you know would have access to or rights to or so
on, therefore you are not obligated. Okay, so that so the presumably
the underlying reason.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay, let
me hold on. ורמינהי *v'reminhi*, and I'll ask you on this: פרה
המרכסת בתבואה אינו עובר משום בל תחסום *Para hamerakeses bitvuah eino over
mishum bal sachsom*.
So we have a ברייתא braisa *braisa* that teaches again that these
cows that are מרכסות *merakesos*, whatever that means, in grain, wander over
the grain, you don't transgress muzzling your ox. והדשות בתרומה ומעשר עובר
משום בל תחסום *V'hadasos bitruma u'maaser over mishum bal sachsom*. But if
they are dealing with תרומה truma. *truma* and מעשר maaser. *maaser*, you
are transgressing the prohibition of muzzling. So how do you explain that?
And again, right, תרומות trumos *trumas* and מעשרות masros. *maasros* there too
reasons you should not be transgressing. One is it's already reached the
stage of גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha* for תרומה truma, *truma* and מעשר
maaser *maaser*, right? We said that there's a scenario where it hasn't,
but in a normal case where it has reached that stage, that
puts it out of the category of בל תחסום *bal sachsom*. That's
number one. And number two is whatever the reasons we had before,
לא תחסום lo tachsom שור בדישו bedisho, *Lo sachsom shor b'disho*. So
here however this ברייתא braisa *braisa* somehow feels that you do transgress
בל תחסום *bal sachsom*. So how do we deal with that? עובר
משום בל תחסום *Over mishum bal sachsom*. So we're going to reconcile
that in a minute, but let's first finish reading the ברייתא braisa
*braisa*. ונכרי הדש בפרתו של ישראל Yisrael, אינו עובר משום בל תחסום
*V'nochri hadash b'paraso shel Yisrael eino over mishum bal sachsom*. If a
non-Jew is you know threshing with your cow, then you don't transgress
the prohibition of בל תחסום *bal sachsom*. Now רש"י *Rashi* says that
we're talking that he's threshing his grain. Now of course the non-Jew
doesn't transgress, the non-Jew isn't prohibited. So we have to ask then
how could you transgress? I mean it's not like maybe you would
have thought that it's like שבת Shabbat? *Shabbos*, you know, that you
have to make sure your animal isn't muzzled, and maybe that's what
it's saying. But since the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is sort of you
know commanding the owner, or commanding the person, לא תחסום lo tachsom
שור בדישו bedisho *Lo sachsom shor b'disho*, רש"י *Rashi* says that the
scenario here is that you told the non-Jew to muzzle it, and
you still do not transgress. Now רש"י *Rashi* says it's when they're
doing their grain. רש"י *Rashi* suggests that if the non-Jew is your
worker and you know working in your grain and in your field
and threshing your grain and you told him to muzzle it you
would transgress, which we'll see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
a little later on, that's an interesting question. Okay, but if the
if just because it's your cow, you don't transgress, it's not like
שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*, you have to ensure that your cow rests, and
whether you tell the non-Jew and is that a type of a
sense of שליחות shlichus. *shlichus* and an extension of you, or we'll
see in a minute how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to deal
with that. Let's hold off for a second. וישראל דש בפרתו של
נכרי עובר משום בל תחסום. But if you however are using a
non-Jew's cow, it doesn't matter, it's not the question of the cow,
it's that you are the Jew are muzzling a cow when it
is threshing. And interesting to think here that if it means in
the, you know, if would this mean that even if I was
a hired hand to work in the field of a non-Jew, and
the non-Jew was telling and it was a non-Jew's cow, and the
non-Jew's grain, and the non-Jew was telling me you have to muzzle
it, right, nevertheless, I'm transgressing. It's not about my grain or my
cow, it's about me muzzling an ox when it is threshing. Or
do we say the word בדישו bedisho and again the possessive is
going on the ox presumably not the owner, but can we read
בדישו bedisho. similar to the way we excluded תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros
right, was that because it wasn't the owner the דישו disho of
the cow or was it the דישו disho of the owner? So
what happens if it's not my grain and if it's the non-Jew's
grain, would that also be a basis for exclusion? Fascinatingly not discussed
in the גמרא. Gemara But we're going to focus in on the
תרומות trumos and the מעשרות. maisros. Okay.
So, the גמרא Gemara says like this, קשיא תרומה אתרומה קשיא מעשר
אמעשר, kashya truma atruma kashya maser amaser, so it's a contradiction, right,
our ברייתא braisa teaches there's no prohibition by תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros
and this ברייתא braisa teaches there is a prohibition, and we'll look
at each one separately, two contradictions, one about תרומה truma and one
about מעשר. maaser? בשלמא תרומה אתרומה לא קשיא, bishlama truma atruma lo
kashya, תרומה truma. against תרומה truma is not a problem, כאן בתרומה
כאן בגידולי תרומה. kan betruma kan begidulei truma. When it says there
is a, there's no prohibition, that's when it's genuine תרומה truma and
since genuine תרומה truma as, you know, תוספות Tosafot has pointed out,
again we'll just use תוספות'ס Tosafos's reasoning here, since genuine תרומה truma
is not something, unless you're dealing with vetch and כרשינים, karshinim, is
not something that is considered something that the cow has rights to,
it's not the דישו disho of the cow, right, it's either has
to be brought to ירושלים Yerushalayim, and eaten there, or even if
it's מעשר שני, maaser sheni if it's תרומה, truma oh, sorry, we're
talking about תרומה, truma if it's תרומה, truma even if it's a
cow of a כהן, kohen if it's not vetch, then it shouldn't
be eaten by cows, it should be eaten by humans. So it's
not considered the דישו dishau. of the cow. That's by תרומה. truma,
But by גידולי תרומה, gidulei truma, what's גידולי תרומה? gidulei truma? גידולי
תרומה Gidulei truma is you give a bag of grain to a
כהן kohen for תרומה, truma and then the כהן kohen. rather than
grinding it and making flour and baking it, decides to plant it
in his field for the next year, and then grain grows from
that. And then grain grows from that and then you harvest that
grain and you take תרומות ומעשרות, the grain that's left after you
took תרומות ומעשרות that grew from תרומה truma, seeds is not itself
תרומה. truma Once the seed decomposes and a new stalk of grain
grows from it, it no longer has its status of תרומה truma.
from the תורה, Torah, דרבנן derabbanan they said that you had to
sort of treat it as תרומה terumah because they did not want
it to, you to be leaving it around and waiting for the
next season in order to plant it, and then you would come
and wind up eating it not within the parameters that תרומה truma,
can be eaten, when you're טמא tamei or other types of concern,
so you would let it become טמא tamei etc. Okay, so that's
only rabbanically תרומה truma. and therefore we say that the prohibition does
apply because the rabbinic status of תרומה truma, is not going to
get you out of your biblical prohibition not to muzzle the cow.
Okay, so where it does apply is by גידולי תרומה gidulei truma
which is not תרומה truma, from the תורה'ס Torah's perspective.
כאן בתרומה כאן בגידולי תרומה. kan betruma kan begidulei truma. That's according
to the, so if the לא תחסום lo tachsom applies, it doesn't
apply to normal תרומה truma that's not בדישו, bedisho that's not the
type of threshing the food that is fit for the cow, but
it does apply to
גידולי תרומה. gidulei truma. All right. אלא מעשר אמעשר קשיא. ela maser
amaser kashya. What are you going to do about the contradiction about
מעשר? maaser Because there's no status of גידולי מעשר. gidulei maaser. The
rabbinic law, they would not call גידולי מעשר gidulei maaser מעשר, maaser
they would call גידולי מעשר gidulei maaser חולין. chullin. The rabbis only
made this category of גידולי תרומה gidulei truma by תרומה, truma not
by מעשר. maaser, וכי תימא מעשר אמעשר נמי לא קשיא, vechi teima
maser amaser nami lo kashya, you'll say that's not a problem, כאן
במעשר כאן בגידולי מעשר, kan bemaser kan begidulei maser, ah I jumped
ahead, the גמרא Gemara already says that, let's say oh maybe it's
the same distinction. בשלמא גידולי תרומה תרומה, bishlama gidulei truma truma, no,
because stuff that grows from תרומה truma is at least דרבנן'ly derabbananly
תרומה, trumah so that's why the ברייתא braisa could call it תרומה
trumah and say לא תחסום lo tachsom still applies because the rabbis
gave it a status of תרומה. trumah אלא גידולי מעשר חולין נינהו,
ela gidulei maser chullin ninhu, but stuff that grows from מעשר maiser
even דרבנן'ly derabbananly is considered to be just straight חולין chullin and
therefore the ברייתא braisa would never have called it מעשר. maiser דתנן,
detnan, we learned in the משנה, mishna, גידולי טבל וגידולי מעשר שני
חולין, gidulei tevel vegidulei maser sheni chullin, that let's say for let's
say it's not even גידולי תרומה, gidulei truma, let's say you took
grain when it was still טבל, tevel, you didn't separate out תרומות
ומעשרות and you planted it and stuff grew from it, and then
you harvested it and took תרומות ומעשרות, the stuff that would remain
would be חולין. chullin. Okay, the only thing that after you
planted... So אלא, ella, so the ברייתא braisa would not have called
that מעשר. maiser, So you've got one ברייתא braisa that says מעשר
maiser. there is no issue of לא תחסום lo tachsom and that
we said is because it is מעשר שני maaser sheni. and מעשר
שני maaser sheni you have to eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim and it
is not really yours and the cow does not really have—it is
not really fit for the cow, so we would not call it
דישו. dishau But what about the ברייתא Braisa that says you do
transgress לא תחסום lo tachsom? by מעשר? maiser So it says like
this: אלא לא קשיא, ella lo kashya, it is not difficult. הא
במעשר ראשון הא במעשר שני. ha b'maaser rishon ha b'maaser sheni. Ah,
that is a nice easy answer, right? Because we have been saying
מעשר שני maaser sheni we understand has to be eaten in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim according to some opinions it is ממון גבוה. mamon gavoh That
is the ברייתא Braisa, that says it is not דישו dishau, and
you are exempt. The ברייתא braisa that says that you are חייב
chayav is normal מעשר ראשון maaser rishon which is given to a
לוי levi and that has no special status—I mean it is owned
by a לוי levi but no special halakhic status and therefore you
do transgress.
Okay, הא במעשר שני. ha b'maaser sheni. ואיבעית אימא, v'ibayis eima, if
you want I can say הא והא במעשר שני. ha v'ha b'maaser
sheni. Let us say something even more interesting. Both ברייתות braisas are
talking about מעשר שני. maaser sheni ולא קשיא, v'lo kashya, הא רבי
מאיר הא רבי יהודה. ha Rabbi Meir ha Rabbi Yehuda. Now we
are going to get to this איסור issur of whether מעשר שני
maaser sheni is considered ממון גבוה mamon gavoh or ממון הדיוט. mamon
hedyot. הא רבי מאיר דאמר מעשר שני ממון גבוה הוא, ha Rabbi
Meir d'amar maaser sheni mamon gavoh hu, that מעשר שני maaser sheni
is God's own—is God's property, meaning yes, you have the right to
control it and to bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim, and eat it,
but when you are eating it, you are eating that which belongs
to God. That is conceptually what it is about. And and and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, הא רבי יהודה דמעשר שני ממון הדיוט
הוא. ha Rabbi Yehuda d'maaser sheni mamon hedyot hu. It is it
is ממון הדיוט. mamon hedyot. Now what difference does that make? They
both agree you have to bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim, and eat
it there. What makes the difference if let us say you want
to use it for another purpose? If I want to give מעשר
שני maiser sheini to a woman and use it as money for
קידושין. kiddushin. Now, it is something that has value, this woman could
go ahead and take it and eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim? I
have given her something of value, but did I give her something
that was mine? For רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you did not. You—it
was already—belonged to God and you just had control and access to
it and now you gave control and access to it to this
woman, but you did not give her your money and therefore she
is not מקודשת. mekudeshet. So here too that would affect whether you
would—whether it would be considered דישו, dishau. that possessive. Okay, even though—again
the possessive is about the cow it seems to be. Okay, that
would be—now, you know, why didn't you just—now it is a little
bit interesting, right? Because if it is out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim then
whether it is your money or the cow's—when—God's money, the cow should
not—you do not have a right for—to allow the cow to eat
it. So are we talking in ירושלים? Yerushalayim. Let us take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara says. But certainly that basic discussion
of מעשר maiser of ממון גבוה mamon gavoh. and ממון הדיוט mamon
hedyot would seem to affect this question, you know, the more it
is God's money, the less it is דישו. dishau? So let us
see what the גמרא Gemara does with this. היכי דמי? heichi dami?
So that is what the גמרא Gemara says. What's the case? כגון—now
kigon I'm sorry, no, we are going to pause actually we are
going to pause on the ממון גבוה ממון הדיוט mamon gavoh mamon
hedyot first of all and now go step back and figure out
how is this תרומות ומעשרות that it has not that you're—there could
be a problem of לא תחסום lo sachsom? if לא תחסום lo
sachsom. no longer applies once it gets to the stage of being
obligated in תרומות ומעשרות? The issue I raised before. היכי דמי, heichi
dami, what is the case? כגון שתרמו בשבלים, kigon shetarmu b'shibolim, that
you went to the owner of the grain when the grain was
still in the sheaves and you or you know and the stalks
and when it was still in the field and you said 'You're
the כהן kohen. or and you said give me my תרומות ומעשרות
now. You're the כהן, you're the לוי.' levi. The owner separated it
or in the case of מעשר שני maiser sheini, where the owner
does not give it to you, he separated it, but you separated
it all before the גמר מלאכה for the מעשר maiser and תרומות
ומעשרות, before you had threshed and winnowed and put it in a
pile. You went when it was still there in the field and
you got your תרומות ומעשרות then and he separated his מעשר שני
maiser sheini then and that is how it could have that status
before it is נגמר מלאכתו nigmar melachto and while it is still
there in the stalks, then you have your cow thresh it. And
that is the question of at an earlier stage, but it is
תרומה trumah or מעשר, maiser, do you transgress לא תחסום? lo sachsom.
Okay, so that is something we should have raised earlier that the
גמרא Gemara now is finally pointing out now. Okay, now,
now we get back to the ממון גבוה mamon gavoh. or ממון
הדיוט mamon hedyot and how does that play out with this question?
ולרבי יהודה והא
בעי חומה? u'l'Rabbi Yehuda v'ha ba'ei choma?
So the גמרא Gemara says 'I do not get it. Even according
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that it is ממון—that mamon it is
ממון הדיוט—it mamon hedyot is not ממון גבוה. mamon gavoha But you
are not allowed to eat it outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim. and therefore
certainly your cow cannot eat it outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim, So therefore
how do you say it is דישו? disho? How do you say
it is grain that the cow has access to? You do not
even need ממון גבוה.' mamon gavoha, It's not grain that the cow
is allowed to be eating. והא בעי חומה? veha ba'ei choma? So
it says כגון שדש לפנים מחומת בית פגי. kegon shedash lifnim mechomas
Beis Pagi. Okay, you threshed it inside the wall of בית פגי
Beis Pagi which was like the outer wall of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
we're talking about a case, you brought your מעשר שני maiser sheini
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim you had your cow thresh it. It is בדישו,
b'disho, it is allowed to be eaten now.
Okay, and the what do you call it and the only issue
is the debate of רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה Rebbi Meir veRebbi Yehuda
of is it considered G-d's money or your money? If it's G-d's
money, then that would not be בדישו b'disho. and that's the issue.
But you are allowed to eat it. Alright, so now the גמרא
Gemara says,
where were we?
מחומת
בית פגי. mechomas Beis Pagi. אי בעית אימא ibayisaim if you want
לא קשיא. lo kashya.
כאן במעשר ודאי כאן במעשר דמאי. kan bemaiser vadai kan bemaiser demai.
Ah, here's another distinction. It's מעשר שני, maiser sheini again, we would
still have to be talking inside the walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim Those
were points that could have been made earlier before we got into
the whole רבי
מאיר ורבי יהודה. Rebbi Meir Rebbi Yehuda. And maybe this is working,
you know,
well actually let me take that back. Could be we're talking outside
the walls of ירושלים Yerushalayim, and that's why מעשר שני maiser sheini
is not בדישו b'disho, because you don't have a right to eat
it. So what is the opinion of the ברייתא braisa that says
you are חייב chayiv in לא תחסום? lo sachsom. That we're talking
about מעשר maiser of דמאי. demai. When you take מעשר ma'aser, from
דמאי, demai, דמאי demai is grain that an עם הארץ am ha'aretz
has harvested and he's selling this on the you know he's selling
the grain or he's selling the flour whatever he's selling and we
are concerned that he did not take מעשרות. maisros תרומות we assume
that it's like one little tiny bit from the entire warehouse of
grain so we assume that even the עם הארץ am ha'aretz took
תרומה, trumah but מעשר, ma'aser, which is a tenth and then there's
two מעשרות maisros. so it's 20% we're afraid they did not take
it. So grain that we buy from עם הארץ am ha'aretz is
called דמאי. demai. And even though the majority do take it, so
מן התורה min hatorah you can assume that it was
taken. Rabbinically we have to assume it wasn't taken and we're obligated
to separate off מעשר. ma'aser So but that's only again remember Rabbinic.
So a Rabbinic status cannot exempt you from the prohibition of לא
תחסום. lo tachsom. So if it is מעשר ודאי maiser vadai and
מעשר שני maiser sheini let's say it's outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim. that
you know you're not allowed to eat it, fine, that's why it's
not בדישו. b'disho, But if it is מעשר שני maiser sheini of
דמאי, demai, then even though Rabbinically you treat it as מעשר שני
ma'aser sheini, and you're not allowed to eat it outside of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim from the תורה Torah we should assume that the עם הארץ
am ha'aretz already took תרומות and מעשרות. maisros So from the תורה
Torah's perspective this is not מעשר שני ma'aser sheini and therefore it
is בדישו b'disho. and therefore you are prohibited from לא תחסום. lo
tachsom. So the Rabbinic חומרא chumra of making this like מעשר שני
ma'aser sheini when it's דמאי demai can't make be a קולא kula
to get you out of your obligation of לא תחסום. lo takhsom,
Alright so let's take a
look. כאן במעשר ודאי כאן במעשר דמאי. kan bemaiser vadai kan bemaiser
demai. So now the גמרא Gemara says, השתא דאתית להכי, hasha de'asis
lehachi, now that you gave that answer, you came to that answer,
we can go back to what we were discussing about תרומה. trumah
תרומה תרומה נמי לא קשיא. truma truma nami lo kashya. This is
also an answer for us about תרומה, trumah, we don't have to
talk about what do you call it about
גידולי תרומה. gidulei truma. כאן בתרומת ודאי כאן בתרומת דמאי. kan betrumas
vadai kan betrumas demai. It's a difference between normal תרומה, trumah regular
תרומה trumah and תרומת דמאי. trumas demai. Of course the גמרא Gemara.
has just really said it in order to dismiss it because now
the גמרא Gemara responds. One minute, בשלמא מעשר דמאי איכא, bishlama maiser
demai ika, there is such a thing of מעשר ma'aser of דמאי,
demai, אלא תרומה דמאי מי איכא? ella truma demai mi ika? There's
no such thing of תרומה trumah of דמאי, demai, you don't take
תרומה terumah from דמאי, demai, which is very funny I mean that's
ABCs the גמרא Gemara obviously knew that. והתניא vehatanya we learned in
a ברייתא, beraita אף הוא af hu even he and here we're
talking about יוחנן כהן גדול, Yochanan Kohen Gadol, ביטל את הוידוי, bittel
es havidui, he said that you no longer do the וידוי vidui
when you take the מעשרות maisros out of the house ביערתי הקדש
מן הבית וגם נתתיו ללוי, bi'arti hakodesh min habayis vegam nesativ lalevi,
he said we have to stop saying that because in his time
after עזרא Ezra they made a תקנה takana because since the לוויים
Leviim did not come up in the return from בבל לארץ ישראל
Bavel le-Eretz Yisrael in the second בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that they
would no longer give מעשר ma'aser. to the לוי, Levi, they would
only give it to the כוהנים. Kohanim. כוהנים Kohanim are also לוויים
Leviim so obviously they fulfilled their obligation, but then you could not
say the וידוי vidui of מעשר ma'aser of אף נתתיו ללוי. af
nesativ lalevi. So he said do not do that וידוי vidui of
מעשר, ma'aser, וגזר על הדמאי, vegazar al hademai, and he was the
one that instituted this idea of דמאי demai that you have to
take מעשרות from grain that you buy from עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz.
לפי ששלח בכל גבול ישראל, lefi sheshalach bechol gevul Yisrael, he did
a whole, you know, he did a survey and he researched, he
did some fact gathering, he sent around all of ישראל, you know,
the country of Israel, וראה שלא היו מפרישים אלא תרומה גדולה בלבד,
ve-ra-a shelo hayu mafrishim ella truma gedola bilvad, and he saw that
they were only be taking תרומה גדולה, truma gedola, they did not
take מעשר ma'aser and therefore
he. Now according to this, it sounds like you definitely have to
take מעשר, ma'aser, but another גמרא Gemara said actually חזקה רוב עמי
הארץ מעשרין הן. chazaka rov amei ha'aretz m'asrin hein. No, the majority
actually do take מעשר, ma'aser so that's why it only has a
rabbinic status of מעשר ma'aser, because מן התורה min haTorah you can
rely on רוב. rov. אלא Ella says the גמרא Gemara fine. לא
קשיא. Lo kashya. So now, okay, we have an answer. The מעשר
answer is either the difference between מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon and מעשר
שני, ma'aser sheini or it's between מעשר שני ma'aser sheini whether it's
ממון גבוה or ממון הדיוט, mamon hedyot, and we're talking within ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. You could have maybe said that it's a difference between מעשר
שני ma'aser sheini out of ירושלים Yerushalayim and in ירושלים. Yerushalayim, Or
it's a question of מעשר שני out of ירושלים and whether it's
מעשר שני of דמאי demai or not because if it's דמאי, demai,
it's only a rabbinic status. That doesn't get you out of לא
תחסום. lo tachsom So we got a couple of answers by מעשר.
By תרומה the only way to reconcile it so far is the
difference about גידולי תרומה, gidulei trumah, but now the גמרא's Gemara going
to try to find, you know, normal תרומה you're exempt, it's not
בדישו, b'disho גידולי תרומה gidulei trumah is only a rabbinic status and
therefore it is בדישו. b'disho, But now the גמרא's Gemara going to
try another answer.
Where were we? אלא לא
קשיא כאן בתרומת מעשר ודאי כאן בתרומת מעשר דמאי. Ella lo kashya
kan b'trumas ma'aser vadai kan b'trumas ma'aser demai. Ah, we can still
use the דמאי demai answer and say by תרומה we're not talking
about the normal תרומה that's, you know, the little bit that you
can take over an entire granary, you know, warehouse full. That's given
to the כהן for the very first separating. That's normal תרומה and
that you would not have to take from דמאי, demai, but there
is a type of a תרומה you would have to take from
דמאי. demai. What would it be? תרומת מעשר. Trumas ma'aser. If after
you give the מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon to the לוי, Levi, the
לוי Levi then has to take a tenth of that tenth, a
tenth of his מעשר and give it to the כהן and that's
called תרומת מעשר. trumas ma'aser. So since they did not take מעשר,
they obviously did not take תרומת מעשר, trumas ma'aser, right? So by
דמאי demai you still, even though there's no תרומת דמאי, trumas demai,
there is תרומת מעשר trumas ma'aser of דמאי. demai. Once you give
your מעשר of דמאי demai to the לוי, Levi, the לוי Levi
then goes ahead and then the לוי, Levi, you know, will take
the תרומת מעשר, trumas ma'aser, okay?
So whoever's taking it. Once you separate out the מעשר, the מעשר
then the taking of the תרומה, the תרומת מעשר trumas ma'aser goes
to the whatever goes to the כהן. So we could be talking
about a case where is תרומה still a case of בדישו, b'disho
it only has a rabbinic status. Not תרומת דמאי, trumas demai, תרומת
דמאי trumas demai doesn't exist, but תרומת מעשר trumas ma'aser of דמאי,
demai, that does exist and that's only rabbinic. So therefore it would
not get you out of the prohibition of שור בדישו. So we're
able to use the דמאי demai answer for תרומה in this case
of תרומת מעשר. trumas ma'aser. Okay. Fine. So that is the end
of that discussion. Bottom line is that this idea we're talking about
number one a case where you separated out תרומות ומעשרות before it
was threshed and before it was נגמר מלאכתו, nigmar melachto, which you're
able to do. And then you're exempt when it is a case
of normal תרומה because it's not בדישו, the cow doesn't you don't
have a right to give it to the cow. When it's מעשר
שני because it's not considered owned by you, ממון גבוה, or because
it's not in ירושלים, the cow doesn't have a right to it
and that's the ברייתא beraita that you're exempt, it's not בדישו. And
the ברייתא braita, that you're חייב chayav are special cases where for
example it only has that status rabbinically, so therefore it's דמאי demai
or it's מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon or something of that nature where
therefore it is בדישו from the תורה's Torah perspective. Okay. Next point.
בעי מיניה מרב ששת. Ba'ei minei me-Rav Sheshes. They asked of Rav
Sheshes: היתה אוכלת ומתרזת מהו? Haysa ocheles u-mesarzes mahu? Let's say an
animal you would let it be eating while it was, you know,
you weren't muzzling it, but as it would eat that would actually
it had some stomach issues and that would actually cause it to
be like have, you know, to be relieving itself. It had diarrhea,
okay? So it was and as it would eat it actually would
be bad, it would cause it to have this bad effect on
it. So what's the story? So do you have to are you
allowed to muzzle it? That would actually be better for it to
muzzle it. So this is really, really fascinating because here there's no
word in the פסוק pasuk that we could דרשן. darshan. Maybe we
could say בדישו, maybe בדישו means when it's for its benefit, not
when it's not for its benefit, okay? But it sounds like the
גמרא Gemara even without any basis in the פסוק pasuk is saying
what's the principle about, what is the reason תורה Torah says don't
muzzle it? And if I can figure out what that reason is,
that will let me tell me whether it applies in this case
or not. Normally, even when we try to understand the reason, it
guides us to interpret the words of the פסוק pasuk, that would
exclude this case. But here it's an ox threshing and you would
the גמרא's Gemara saying maybe you would be allowed to muzzle it
because in this case it's not to its benefit and maybe what
the principle is about is about the animal's benefit. Fascinating גמרא. Gemara
So מהו? mahu? What's the story? משום דמעלי להו mishum dema'ale leihu
והא לא מעלי לה? vaha lo ma'ale lah? Is the reason
you're not supposed to muzzle it because it's to its benefit, and
here it's, you know, and here it's not to its benefit to
leave it
unmuzzled? Or would you say דחזו מצטערא, de-chazu mitztara, it's not because
the eating is to its
benefit that you can't muzzle it, it's because seeing the grain in
front of it and not being allowed to chew from it causes
it, you know, distress. So it's not like it has a right
to eat and you want to give, you know, and you're feeding
it and you should be feeding your cow, it's the distress that
comes from it being muzzled when the grain is in front of
it. And that distress will exist even in this case as well.
והא חזו מצטערא, vaha chazu mitztara, it's distressed, you know, it doesn't
sort of think abstractly like oh if I eat it it's going
to be bad for me, it's going to cause me, you know,
to have runs and therefore I'm not distressed. I mean humans also,
they could know that something is bad for them and if they're
not able to eat it they feel, that you know that causes
distress. So אמר להו amar leihu רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, so רב
ששת Rav Sheshet said תניתוה, tanituha, we taught it in a בריתא.
baraita. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, אומר מביא כשינין
ותולה לה שהכשינין יפה לה מן הכל. meivi khashinin u-tolah lah she-khashinin
yafeh lah mikol. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי, בר
יוחאי bar Yochai said that when you have to address the מראית
עין mar'it ayin case of like a cow threshing in תרומה and
מעשר, you give it this vetch because the vetch is the best
for it of all the things it could eat. So he's, even
though that's addressing just a מראית עין mar'it ayin case, the fact
that he brings in that consideration of what would be the best
for the cow—why do you care what would be the best for
the cow? You're addressing מראית עין, mar'it ayin, you know, you're not
telling me under other circumstances what my diet for my cow should
be. Why here are you giving me advice about what my diet
for my cow should be? It must be that this idea of
what's best for it is part of what is going on within
the prohibition of muzzling it. So now that we're talking about addressing
an issue about, you know, about okay מראית עין mar'it ayin etc.
about muzzling, you're going to raise the value of what is best
for it. So you see that for רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai, the value of what is best for it is
the driving principle here. That's what the גמרא Gemara says. שמע מינה
משום דמעלי לה הוא שמע מינה. shema mina mishum dema'ale lah hu,
shema mina. You see that the issue is because what is best
for it and that's what you see from here. So this is
quite fascinating because again to repeat, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai is just saying his point around addressing a מראית עין
mar'it ayin case and okay, he mentions that it's best for it,
maybe that's a factor, that doesn't tell you it's the only factor.
And again, he's not really addressing the parameters of לא תחסום. lo
tachsom. So number one it's fascinating that we take our lead from
רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. But the other thing
that's fascinating, as I said, is that without any basis in the
פסוק, pasuk, the גמרא Gemara is saying you are allowed to muzzle
your cow or maybe you should muzzle your cow because in this
circumstance it is actually to its detriment to be unmuzzled. We are
going to decide that the reason of the פסוק, even though there's
two legitimate options—it's not even the self-evident
reason—it could be because of whether it's to its benefit to be
unmuzzled or could be whether it causes its distress, you know, when
it's muzzled, but we are going to decide that it's because of
its benefit and we're going to say that you're allowed to muzzle
it in this case. Quite quite fascinating. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. איבעיא
להו, iba'ya lehu, they ask a question: מהו שיאמר אדם לנכרי חסום
פרתי ודוש בה? mahu she-yomar adam le-nokhri chasom parati ve-dosh bah? Can
you tell a non-Jew to muzzle your ox and thresh? Now this
is exactly the case before where it said you do not transgress
if you tell a non-Jew to muzzle. רש"י says it is talking
about he's threshing his grain. From רש"י it would sound like if
he was threshing your grain, it definitely would be prohibited. But תוספות
Tosafot understands no no no, we're talking about your grain because we're
going to see that the גמרא Gemara is going to compare it
to other cases of like אמירה לנכרי, amirah le-nokhri, like if I
tell a non-Jew could you light a fire for me on שבת?
Shabbat Okay, and that clearly is to benefit me. So here too
we're talking about telling the non-Jew to muzzle my cow when he's
threshing my grain. Let's say this non-Jew is my
employee. Alright? And that's the question. Alright? Whereas תוספות Tosafot says that
if you tell a non-Jew to do something for the non-Jew's benefit
that you're not allowed to do, that's totally okay. And he says
like can I tell a non-Jew who works for me, here's some
food, go ahead and you know like I have to, I have
to feed them on שבת, Shabbat, can I give them some raw
food and say here's some food, feel free to go ahead and
cook it for yourself or so on. Okay, anyway but let's talk
about that's a and he, you know, he discusses whether that's exactly
parallel to this case or not. But we're going to assume the
simple case not like רש"י but like תוספות says that you're asking
the non-Jew to muzzle your cow and to thresh your grain. Is
that allowed or not? Okay so let's take a look. איבעיא. iba'ya.
מהו לומר לנכרי חסום פרתי ודוש בה? mahu lomer lenokhri khasom parati
u'dosh bah? מי אמרינן, Mi-amrinan, do we say, כי אמרינן ki amrinan
אמירה לנכרי amira lenokhri שבות, shvut, הני מילי hani milei בשבת? b'shabat?
When do we say that it's a rabbinic prohibition, and even the
word שבות shvut as a שבת Shabbat word to have a non-Jew
tell a non-Jew to do something for you, that only applies to
שבת, Shabbat דאיסורא סקילה, de-isura sekilah, which is prohibited by stoning, right?
It's a very weighty prohibition. Also, you know, there's a broader sense
on שבת Shabbat. that מלאכה is being done on your behalf,
and all of that. So it's maybe a particularly שבת Shabbat. idea.
אבל חסימה דאיסור לאו לא, aval khasima de-isur lav lo, but by
muzzling, which is only a simple negative prohibition, it would not apply.
או דילמא לא שנא, o dilma lo shana, or maybe it doesn't
matter, we always... and so this is a huge question even though
we're in the middle of all this stuff which seems highly particular
to the issue of לא תחסום, lo tachsom this is a huge
question of something I am not allowed to do, can I have
a non-Jew do it for me? Okay, and that's the question. Can
I have a non-Jew go ahead and muzzle my cow for me?
תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here, what we taught earlier: נכרי
הדוש בפרתו של ישראל, nokhri hadosh be-parato shel Yisrael, if a non-Jew
is using a Jew's cow, אינו עובר משום לא תחסום, eino over
mishum lo takhsom, he's not transgressing. And we're assuming that the case
is not that the non-Jew rented my cow and he's making his
own decisions. We're assuming it's our case. I told him to muzzle
it and I still don't transgress and even as תוספות says, presumably
even in a case where he's threshing my grain, I would not
transgress. So the גמרא Gemara says no, that doesn't prove it. מעבד
הוא דלא עבד. ma-avehu de-lo avar. I'm sorry, excuse me, the גמרא
Gemara tries to prove that that it is rabbinically prohibited from that.
So גמרא Gemara says מעבד הוא דלא עבד, ma-avehu de-lo avar, it
says I don't transgress the biblical prohibition. הא איסורא איכא? hai isura
ika? It's still rabbinically forbidden. It didn't say it's permissible for me
to have the non-Jew do it, it just says I don't biblically
transgress. Okay, so it sounds like it's still a rabbinic problem. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, בדין הוא דאיסורא נמי ליכא. bedin hu
de-isura nami leka. No, it could be that that's totally
permitted. ואיידי דתני סיפא, ve-adai de-tani seifa, since it taught at the
end: ישראל הדוש בפרתו של נכרי עובר, Yisrael hadosh be-parato shel nokhri
over, that if a Jew uses a non-Jew's cow, he does transgress,
תני רישא אינו עובר, tani reisha eino over, it teaches in the
beginning that he does not transgress when it is a non-Jew doing
it with my cow. So that ברייתא was only talking about the
question of is it a biblical transgression. It says for a Jew
to do it with a non-Jew's cow, it is. I think it's
still an interesting question whether that would apply even if the Jew
was working for the non-Jew and threshing the grain of the non-Jew,
would that still be considered דישו? disho But it sounds like if
דישו is the cow's דישה, disha, then maybe yes. So that would
be really interesting, limiting a Jew's ability to work for a non-Jew
and to do the actual muzzling. We'll see later if somebody else
muzzles it, can the Jew go ahead and have the ox a-threshing
while it's already muzzled. Okay, so the fact that it's the non-Jew's
cow and maybe even the non-Jew's grain doesn't matter, the Jew still
transgresses when the Jew does it. But for a Jew to have
a non-Jew do it does not biblically transgress. Okay, it's telling the
Jew you do not muzzle it, so having the non-Jew do it
for you is not a דאורייתא d'Oraita prohibition, but it does not
answer our question whether there still is a rabbinic prohibition of אמירה
לגוי amira le-goy to have it done. And that is a general
question by all איסורים, issurim, is there a rabbinic prohibition of אמירה
לגוי? amira le-goy? And that we don't know, the ברייתא was only
talking about the Torah prohibition. So let's keep on going. תא שמע,
Ta shema, come in here: דשלחו ליה לאבוה דשמואל, de-shakhu le-avuha de-shmuel,
they sent to the father of שמואל Shmuel from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael the following message: הלין תורי, halin tore, these oxen, דגנבין ארמאי,
de-ganvin aramaei, that non-Jews steal, ומנכניין יתהון, u-menakhniyan yathon,
and they basically sterilize them, castrate them, that's the word. מהו? mahu?
What's the הלכה? Halacha, Is that allowed or not? So apparently what
would happen is, and this is a very big issue nowadays about
spaying and neutering animals, there is a prohibition against ובארצכם לא תעשו
u-ve'artzechem lo ta'asu of neutering animals and cutting off their genitals. But
that would be something that you would standard do for a case
of
a in farming that you would castrate an ox. When you castrate
an ox, that's what makes it a bull, I believe that's the
way it goes, and it just makes it more usable for the
farm. I actually think I might have gotten it wrong, I forget
which way I just said it, but actually I think that it's
an ox that is the castrated bull. Anyway, okay, so when we
talk about oxen that are plowing and so on, it's because once
the bull is castrated, it now actually, you know, it affects its
strength and it becomes stronger. longer and that actually is what's more
useful in the farm. So what are you going to do? You're
a farmer, you've got these male cows, these bulls, you want them
castrated. You're not allowed to, so they devised a whole little type
of a trick, you know, a, that non-Jews would come in the
middle of the night at my behest, with my understanding, and they
would take my bulls, you know, out of the farm, they would
castrate them, and then they would return them. That would be, you
know, what they would do without me directly being involved, quote-unquote. And
they said, is that allowed? All right, שלח להו, Shelach lehu, and
he sent back, הערמה איעביד בהו, Harama isavid behu, they were trying
to do something, some workaround, you know, some, we all know about
הערמהs Haramas like selling your חמץ Chametz or whatever, you know, they
were trying to do some loophole,
and ארימו עלייהו, Irimu alaihu, you do go back on them and
do something sort of like devious to them, or, you know, or
something that undermines what they're trying to do, a הערמה Harama like
is undermining the הלכה, halacha so you do something that undermines what
they were trying to do, ויזדבון, Vizdabun, and you have to make
them sell it. They're not allowed to keep these bulls, so these,
excuse me, these oxen. So maybe the only solution is that, you
know, Jews who have farms have to buy oxen, and, you know,
maybe they can sell their bulls and the people that buy it
castrate it and then they go ahead and buy it back as
oxen, and maybe they have to pay more, but they cannot actually
have this done to their bulls, and if they did, they can't
benefit from it, and we are going to force them to sell
it and to not use it. So you see that it is
prohibited. Now this is actually even more than just אמירה לעכו"ם, Amira
l'akum, this is actually, you know, even if they're just doing it
with a wink and a nod and without me directly even telling
them to do it. So that seems that not only is אמירה
לעכו"ם Amira l'akum prohibited, but even just being done, you know, to,
according to my, because I want it to be done and according
to my wishes, even without me telling them, itself is also prohibited.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב פפא, Amar
Rav Pappa, בני מערבא סברי לה כרבי חידקא. Benei Marva savri lah
k'Rabbi Chidka.
No, that doesn't prove anything. They would hold, those people in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael who sent to שמואל, Shmuel, and I guess שמואל,
Shmuel, or the father of שמואל, Shmuel, the father of שמואל Shmuel
sent back to them, would hold like רבי חידקא, Rabbi Chidka, דאמר
בני נח מצווין על הסירוס, de'amar Benei Noach metzuvin al hasirus, that
says no, that even non-Jews are prohibited against, you know, castrating. It's
part of like the שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvot Benei Noach,
somewhat included in the broader understanding of פרו ורבו, Pru u'revu, וקא
עברי משום לפני עור לא תתן מכשול, veka avrei mishum Lifnei iver
lo titein michshol, and by allowing this trick to take place, the
Jews who are allowing the non-Jew to take it and castrate are
over לפני עור Lifnei iver of the non-Jew because they're trying to
get the non-Jew to do it for them, and for the non-Jew
itself, it's an עבירה. aveira. So we don't really have an answer.
That might be because non-Jews are prohibited on סירוס. sirus. Now,
two points about this. Number one is, as I said, this is
even lesser than a case of שליחות. There's not directly telling them,
and still it was seen to be a problem. And maybe there's
something unique about סירוס sirus because it says, ובארצכם לא תעשו, u've'artzchem
lo ta'asu, in your lands you shall not do. Even though it's
you shall not do, there's a sense about the phenomenon itself being
problematic. So that could be why you might want to understand that
more broadly in the case of סירוס sirus than you would by
other prohibitions. Maybe it's by סירוס sirus we don't want non-Jews doing
it for us, but other things maybe is a different story, it's
more about us doing it, and for somebody else to do it
would be okay. That's one point. The other point is practically speaking,
this is a very big issue because people that have pets and
need them to get spayed and neutered, what do they do? You
know, Jews, if they want this. Can you take it to a
non-Jew? So first of all, if you think that a non-Jew is
prohibited on סירוס, sirus, then you're over, then you transgress לפני עור.
Lifnei iver. But it seems the general position is that non-Jews are
not over on לפני עור, on, are not prohibited in סירוס. sirus
Okay, but how about the issue about אמירה לעכו"ם? Amira l'akum? That's
going to really matter, how do we come out, whether אמירה לעכו"ם
Amira l'akum applies in cases that are beyond שבת. And if it
does, then you would not be able to do it. So would
you be able to do it with a wink and a nod,
which is sort of what happened here? It seems like, okay, in
the end the גמרא Gemara decides that here was maybe they held
that סירוס sirus was prohibited for non-Jews. But if סירוס sirus is
allowed for non-Jews, then maybe if it's not a direct אמירה, amira,
maybe it would be permissible. So is it like, what about an
אמירה דאמירה? amira d'amira? You make an appointment with the person, you
know, at the, at the vet, and you don't directly tell the
doctor, you know, somebody else tells the doctor. So is that like
an אמירה amira of an אמירה, amira, two stages removed? These are
whole questions about how do we deal with this nowadays. Okay, let's
continue.
Okay, now we're going to have a few more, a little more
discussion about having to sell the animals that were castrated before we
get back to our main question.
סבר רבא למימר יזדבון. Savar Rava l'meimar yizdabun. for beef. You can't
sell them for being used in the fields because as oxen because
then you'll have benefitted from the fact that they were castrated.
אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye said back: No, דין שקנס עליהם
מכירה. din she-knas aleihem mechira. No, no, no, you don't have to
make it that they don't even get some of that monetary benefit,
it's a big enough fine that they're not allowed to use the
animals themselves and they have to sell them. Okay, פשיטא, Pshita, now
the גמרא Gemara says it's obviously בנו גדול כי אחר דמי. beno
gadol ke-acher dami. How now we're going to figure out how to
do a הערמה harama on the קנס. knas. And you know, okay,
you could sell it if you're selling it to your adult son,
that's selling it. Didn't say you have to sell it to a
non-Jew, you have to sell it. So you could sell it to
a Jew. So you could sell it to your adult son. All
right, so you could still sort of get around this קנס. knas.
Doesn't mean it's permissible to do it, but you could still get
around it. בנו קטן מאי? Beno katan mai? How about selling it
to your minor son? Can you do that? And then obviously that
would allow you to continue using it.
רב אחא אסר ורב אשי שרי. Rav Acha asar ve-Rav Ashi sharei.
Fine, it's a debate of רב אחא Rav Acha and רב אשי.
Rav Ashi. מריימר Mareimar ומר זוטרא ואמרי לה הנהו תרי חסידי—מריימר and
מר זוטרא, Mar Zutra, and some say two
חסידים—מחליפי אהדדי. When their animals would be castrated, how would they deal
with the fine about selling it? They would just swap, you know,
like people that would swap their פורים סעודהs. Purim seuda Okay, oh,
my cow is castrated, you know, my bull is castrated, your bull
is castrated, I'll give you my bull for your bull and then
they satisfy the requirement of selling. Now, of course, it sounds like
that they were all doing this again still with this wink and
a nod, which just proves the whole reason that this was a
really hard prohibition at that time, you know, and as I said,
it still is today to figure out how to navigate if it's
a problem for non-Jews today. So, you know, תוספות says, no, no,
no, it was talking about a one-time thing that had happened without
their awareness and so on. Of course, how this could happen without
your awareness and the language מחליפי אהדדי machlifi ahadadi. makes it sound
like it's an ongoing thing, and here we're talking about אמוראים Amoraim
or the גמרא Gemara even says חסידים chasidim would do it, it
really raises that question. And there is a way to thread the
needle. If you think that non-Jews are not prohibited on סירוס and
that there is not an issue of אמירה לעכו"ם amira le-akum or
it doesn't apply by אמירה לעכו"ם amira le-akum if you don't directly
tell them and they come and steal it, then in that case
it would be okay. Of course, if that were true, there wouldn't
be a קנס. knas. So they wouldn't be working within the parameters
of the קנס. knas. Okay, anyway, we still have not answered the
question. Okay, and that's really where the גמרא Gemara ends. So it's
this huge question that applies to like every single עבירה aveira in
the תורה. Torah. Can you have a non-Jew do it for you?
All right, and the גמרא Gemara really leaves it as an open
question and maybe yes, maybe no. Could sort of say ספק דרבנן
לקולא, safek de-rabbanan le-kula, you know, the גמרא Gemara doesn't come out
clearly on one side or the other, but that really in general
we, you know, have to be concerned in הלכה with the possibility
that אמירה לעכו"ם amira le-akum applies to עבירות aveiros way beyond שבת.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara asks the following question. בעי
רמי בר חמא: Ba'ei Rami bar Chama: הושיב לה קוץ בפיה מהו?
hoshiv lah kotz be-fiyah mahu? Let's say it got a thorn in
its mouth, okay, and now it can't eat while it's threshing, but
you didn't muzzle it. Is the prohibition of "don't muzzle" require you—meaning
don't allow it to be muzzled—and this isn't even a muzzle—don't allow
it to be in a situation in which, you know, in which
it's unable to eat? So that's the question. Now actually, I jumped
ahead. הושיב לה Hoshiv lah means you put the thorn in its
mouth. So according to that, רב אשי's Rav Ashi question—you know, רמי
בר חמא's Rami bar Chama question might have been: Is that considered
muzzling, or is a muzzle only physically what we call a muzzle,
like this sort of,
whatever, mask over the mouth of the cow? So the גמרא though
assumes that that obviously is a muzzle. הושיב לה חסימה מעלייתא היא.
Hoshiv lah chasima ma'alyata hi. What, if you put the thorn in
its mouth, you've obviously muzzled it. So that's answer number one. It's
not physically a muzzle; it's something that effectively muzzles it. Fine. אלא
ישב לה קוץ בפיה מהו? Ela yashav lah kotz be-fiyah mahu?
Let's say the thorn—let's say it got a thorn in its mouth.
Is your prohibition of לא תחסום lo tachsom. to not allow it
to be threshing with a muzzle
on—and this we've already called this a muzzle—or just tells you that
you're not allowed to place the muzzle on? הירביץ לה ארי מבחוץ
מהו? Hirbitz lah ari mi-bachutz mahu? Let's say you had a lion,
you took a lion and you had a lion right outside the
field and it made it terrified, so it was too afraid to
eat. What would that story be? Now again, from the simple sense
of the question, it could be is that considered a muzzle? It's
not on its mouth even, something completely external to it. But the
גמרא takes it for granted that it is. So the גמרא says:
הירביץ לה חסימה מעלייתא היא. Hirbitz lah chasima ma'alyata hi. What, if
you put the lion there, that's לא תחסום. Lo Tachsom So it's
quite fascinating. רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama might have been asking
what physically constitutes a muzzle, but the גמרא doesn't—accepts that those are
obviously a muzzle. A thorn is a muzzle, a lion that makes
it afraid is a muzzle. Anything that does the effect of preventing
it from eating is a muzzle. So what's—so if that's true, what's
the question? אלא רבא צלא דבי מבחוץ מהו, Ella Rava tzala d'bei
mibachutz mahu, let's say a lion, you know, sat itself down right
near the field. Do you have to chase the lion away? That's
the question.
העמיד בנו מבחוץ מהו, He'emid bno mibachutz mahu, what if you put
the baby of the cow right outside the field and it was
so worried about its baby, it was too distressed in order to
be eating? היתה צמאה למים מהו, Hayta tzmeiah lamayim mahu, let's say
that it was very thirsty and it wasn't able to eat because
it needed water, what's the story? All right, so that's even different,
that's like not even some external thing that's preventing it, that's just
it's not hungry because it's thirsty. But is that considered that you
have to make it in a state where there's nothing that would
prevent it from eating if it would want to? פירס לה קטבליא
על גבי דישא מהו, Peras lah katavlya al gabei deisha mahu, let's
say you put like a leather spread on top of the grain,
so it was threshing but it couldn't see the grain and couldn't
access it. All right, what's that story? That's not doing something to
the animal to prevent it from eating, it's doing something to the
grain. So those are a whole range of questions. And let's see
what the גמרא says. פשוט מהא חדא, Pashut meiha chada, we can
at least conclude one of them. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in a
ברייתא, רשאי בעל הפרה להרעיב פרתו כדי שתאכל מן הדישא הרבה. Rashai
ba'al hapara lehar'iv parato kedei shetochal min hadeisha harbeh.
If I am lending you or renting to you my cow, I
can starve my cow before the day it works for you so
that you help to feed it in the sense that—so I as
the owner of the cow am getting it fed more from your
grain because I did not feed it very much yesterday. I'm allowed
to do that because you're not allowed to muzzle it. ורשאי בעל
הבית להתיר פקיע עמיר לפני הבהמה כדי שלא תאכל. Verashai ba'al habayit
lehatir paki'a amir lifnei habehemah kedei shelo tochal. And what I'm allowed
to do is I'm allowed to go ahead and
spread straw on top of the grain so that when it's threshing
the grain, it will be eating from the straw and not from
the grain itself. I the owner—so you the—I might have mixed up
who I and you is here, but anyway. You who is lending
me my
cow—you who is lending me your cow cannot feed your cow yesterday
so it will be very hungry when I go ahead and I
work it. But I who has the grain and I'm working the
cow and using it to thresh, I can put hay on top
of the grain so it eats the hay and not the grain.
Okay, so the גמרא says isn't that like spreading
the leather mat on top of it and that seems to be
allowed? כדי שלא תאכל מן הדישא הרבה. Kedei shelo tochal min hadeisha
harbeh. So the גמרא says, לא, שאני התם דקאכלה. Lo, shani hatam
deka'achlah. No,
at least it's still eating. I'm not preventing it from eating, I'm
giving it something else to eat from. Okay, so that's different, that's
not like muzzling. But all these other things might be like muzzling
because one way or another they are preventing it from eating. Okay,
now because the גמרא basically took for granted that, you know, the
lion and whatever if I were to do it would be muzzling
and it said the question is that these situations already exist or
that it's very thirsty, you know, that there already is a lion
there and so on, it really becomes a question of whether לא
תחסום means am I just not allowed to actively muzzle it or
do I have to even remove any impediment from it to be
eating, not use it while it is effectively muzzled. And to use
it while it is effectively muzzled is considered the prohibition of לא
תחסום. So that was the first half of the questions. The second
half like spreading the, what do you call it, like it being
thirsty or spreading the mat over it, you know, that would be
different, that would be whether that's really considered muzzling. That's not something,
you know, that I'm doing
that's on the cow itself. Okay, so that's the question and we
don't know an answer. איבעית
אימא—I'm Ibayit eima sorry, where were we? איבעית אימא, Ibayit eima, if
you want
I
could say, רשאי בעל הבית להתיר פקיע עמיר לפני בהמה מעיקרא כדי
שלא תאכל הרבה מן הדישא. Rashai ba'al habayit lehatir paki'a amir lifnei
behemah me'ikara kedei shelo tochal harbeh min hadeisha.
No,
no, no. That what that means is that when that is allowing
it, back to this issue about the opening up the hay, that
means I can spread the hay on it before it starts working.
So that would not be considered like muzzling it because that would
be a state that would already pre-exist and not that I right
now am muzzling it while it actually is threshing. So maybe that's
why that's okay. And but if you spread
the leather mat on it before it started threshing, maybe that would
be okay. But the issue is what are you doing right now
when you are using it? Right now are you muzzling
it? בעי מיניה רבי יונה מן רבי סימאי, Ba'ei mineih Rabbi Yona
min Rebbi Simai, Rabbi Yona asked Simai, חסמה מבחוץ מהו? Chasama mibachutz
mahu? Right, this sort of actually gets to seems to be getting
to the point that we were raising before. Let's say you muzzled
it before it started threshing. What's the story?
שור בדישו אמר רחמנא, Shor bedisho amar Rachmana, don't muzzle an ox
while it is threshing, and I didn't muzzle it while it was
threshing. או דילמא לא תדוש בחסימה אמר רחמנא, O dilma lo tadush
bachasima amar Rachmana, don't thresh while it is muzzled. So it is
not about the act of muzzling, it's about threshing with it in
a state of being muzzled. And that's the issue. And that seems
to have been all the questions before about the thorn and the
whatnot, which is why the answer about whether you spread the thing
on it before it started or after it started was a little
bit strange, because it seems like the questions that were being asked
before were also questions about am I not allowed to thresh with
it while it's in a state of being muzzled? So if spreading
over the leather matters, spreading over the hay is considered a state
of being muzzled, why should it matter if I did it before
or after? That's a little unclear to me. Anyway, אמר ליה מבית
אביך את למד. Amar lei mibeit avicha at lamad. You can learn
this from your father's house, because he was a כהן. יין ושכר
אל תשת אתה ובניך אתך בבואכם, Yayin veshichar al tisht ata uvannecha
itch bevo'achem, do not drink wine and intoxicating liquid when you come
in to serve in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. בבואכם הוא דאסור.
Bevo'achem hu de'asur. So is it only prohibited to be drinking wine
as you're coming into the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? המשתה מאלי שרי?
Hamishteh me'ali sharei? But you can drink it outside the בית המקדש?
Beit HaMikdash? Obviously not, because it says ולהבדיל בין הקודש ובין החול,
Ulehavdil bein hakodesh uvein hachol, you can't be drunk because you
have to be able to distinguish between קודש kodesh and חול, chol,
אמר רחמנא. Amar Rachmana. So it's about the state of being drunk.
אלא מה התם בשעת ביאה לא תהא שכרות הכא נמי בשעת דישה
לא תהא חסימה. Ela mah hatam besha'at bi'ah lo tehe shichrut hacha
nami besha'at disha lo tehe chasima.
So the same way there you can't be drunk at the time
of when you go into the אהל מועד, Ohel Mo'ed, here you
also cannot have the animal that is muzzled while you are threshing
it. So that is a big redefinition, right? So it is therefore
not just don't muzzle the animal, but don't have it
muzzled while you are threshing with it. So that would seem to
answer all those earlier questions about the case about the the thorn
and the whatnot, because it's in a state of being muzzled and
you're threshing with it. So it's not exactly clear how this answer,
which is a really important one that broadens the scope of what
לא תחסום means, does that now resolve those earlier questions? And why
exactly the גמרא distinguished between spreading the hay on it before it
started or after it started, once we're sort of seem to not
be distinguishing right here. So those are parameters that really have to
be worked out, but we do get the important idea that it
is more than just the act of muzzling it, but we will
continue to see this tomorrow in terms of the question of who
gets lashings, which might be a different question in terms of when
you're doing it, what's considered the action or not. So all of
this is to be continued.